<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-US"
    xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
    xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#">
    <id>tag:theconversation.com,2011:/articles</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://theconversation.com"/>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://theconversation.com/articles"/>
    <title>English – The Conversation</title>
    <updated>2022-04-04T03:28:19Z</updated>
    <entry>
        <id>tag:theconversation.com,2011:article/180565</id>
        <published>2022-04-04T03:28:19Z</published>
        <updated>2022-04-04T03:28:19Z</updated>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://theconversation.com/below-the-line-introducing-the-conversations-new-election-podcast-hosted-by-jon-faine-180565"/>
        <title>Below the Line: introducing The Conversation's new election podcast, hosted by Jon Faine</title>
        <content type="html">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://images.theconversation.com/files/455994/original/file-20220404-21-pyyr7o.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;rect=0%2C0%2C7360%2C4912&amp;amp;q=45&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=496&amp;amp;fit=clip" /&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;span class="caption"&gt;                          &lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="attribution"&gt;&lt;span class="source"&gt;SARAH RHODES/AAP&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;From the polls to party spin to election promises, Below the Line is a limited-edition podcast unpacking party lines and policies during the 2022 Australian federal election campaign.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hosting the conversation is award-winning broadcaster and former ABC Melbourne mornings presenter, Jon Faine, now a Vice Chancellor’s Fellow at the University of Melbourne. He’ll be joined by political scientists Anika Gauja and Simon Jackman from the University of Sydney and La Trobe University’s Andrea Carson, to talk about the issues that matter to you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Below the Line is brought to you by The Conversation and La Trobe University twice weekly until polling day.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Listen to the first episode, in which our panel discusses personalities and pre-selections, when the election will likely be called, and the most probable electiondate. Together, our experts outline the issues that are expected to feature prominently during the campaign and the key challenges for the Coalition seeking re-election for a fourth term in government. And tune in to hear why this election campaign is expected to “get dirty”.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Image credit: Sarah Rhodes/AAP&lt;/p&gt;&lt;img src="https://counter.theconversation.com/content/180565/count.gif" alt="The Conversation" width="1" height="1" /&gt;</content>
        <summary>Below the Line is a limited-edition podcast unpacking party lines and policies during the 2022 Australian election campaign. Join presenter Jon Faine and three political scientists for episode one.</summary>
        <author>
            <name>Benjamin Clark, Deputy Engagement Editor, The Conversation</name>
            <foaf:homepage rdf:resource="https://theconversation.com/au/team#benjamin-clark"/>
        </author>
        <rights>Licensed as Creative Commons – attribution, no derivatives.</rights>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <id>tag:theconversation.com,2011:article/180502</id>
        <published>2022-04-04T02:21:07Z</published>
        <updated>2022-04-04T02:21:07Z</updated>
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://theconversation.com/an-easy-going-everyman-with-vulnerability-beneath-the-bravado-the-best-performances-of-bruce-willis-180502"/>
        <title>An easy-going everyman, with vulnerability beneath the bravado: the best performances of Bruce Willis</title>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This year was shaping up to be another busy one for Bruce Willis: three films released already, with another eight in post-production. Willis has become an astonishingly prolific actor, wisecracking his way through direct-to-video genre releases and joining that elite band of 1980s and 1990s multiplex superstars (Nicolas Cage, John Travolta, Sylvester Stallone) whose box office capital had flatlined. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Willis’s recent reviews were uniformly negative. “Phoning it in” became a byword for his post-2012 career choices, after his last critically successful films, Looper and Moonrise Kingdom. Hard Kill (2020), Apex (2021) and A Day to Die (2022) will not live long in the cultural memory. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Willis’s recent decision to step away from acting after a &lt;a href="https://theconversation.com/what-is-aphasia-the-condition-bruce-willis-lives-with-180399"&gt;diagnosis of aphasia&lt;/a&gt; – a language disorder caused by damage in the area of the brain cUnhandled exception.ontrolling language expression and comprehension – brings his career to a cruel end. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;  &lt;em&gt;    &lt;strong&gt;      Read more:      &lt;a href="https://theconversation.com/what-is-aphasia-the-condition-bruce-willis-lives-with-180399"&gt;What is aphasia, the condition Bruce Willis lives with?&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;In his day, Willis could still surprise and tantalise. Terry Gilliam, who, in 12 Monkeys (1995), directed Willis in  one of his most complex performances as the time traveller tasked with saving the world from a deadly virus, once &lt;a href="https://www.theringer.com/movies/2021/1/5/22213761/12-monkeys-terry-gilliam-history_"&gt;described him&lt;/a&gt; as “a guy who was vulnerable, a man who’s lost, not the man in charge of the whole thing”.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is this paradox – helplessness and resilience – that has defined Willis’s screen persona for four decades.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Vulnerability beneath the bravado&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 1988, one of Hollywood’s most laser-focused high concept pitches – NYPD cop saves hostages in a skyscraper on Christmas Eve – gave Willis the chance to hit the stratosphere. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As John McClane in Die Hard he almost single-handedly defined the wise-cracking action hero in the late 1980s, bringing an everyman quality to his roles that made up for in quips and smirks what he lacked in the hardened muscularity of a Jean-Claude van Damme or an Arnold Schwarzenegger. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Willis would return to the Die Hard franchise every few years. The law of diminishing returns inevitably kicked in, but the original played up Willis’s vulnerability beneath the bravado. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;            &lt;iframe width="440" height="260" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/jaJuwKCmJbY?wmode=transparent&amp;amp;start=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;                      &lt;/figure&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;  &lt;em&gt;    &lt;strong&gt;      Read more:      &lt;a href="https://theconversation.com/nine-reasons-why-die-hard-really-is-a-christmas-film-173801"&gt;Nine reasons why Die Hard really is a Christmas film&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;For a time, Willis could always be relied upon when heroism was wanted. Need someone to climb to the roof of a church and save two kids in the middle of a lightning storm?  Wes Anderson, in the delightfully off-beat Moonrise Kingdom (2012), knew just the man. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Need someone to lead a crack team of oil drillers into space and blow up an asteroid headed for Earth?  Michael Bay’s Armageddon (1998) – the high watermark of impending planetary disaster films – might not have worked as well were it not for Willis’s deadly seriousness at the centre of this madcap plot. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(And I wonder if it was his idea to have his character introduced by hitting golf balls off an oil-rig and using a Greenpeace protest boat as target practice?  It certainly fits the devil-may-care persona Willis honed over his time in Hollywood.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;            &lt;iframe width="440" height="260" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/luakVLOQwD4?wmode=transparent&amp;amp;start=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;                      &lt;/figure&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Willis’s most interesting performances&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Country (1989) is Exhibit A when listing Willis’s bona fides as an actor.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Light years away from John McClane, and a tantalising glimpse of what he was capable of when given a good script and a no-nonsense director, Willis plays a Kentucky Vietnam vet struggling with PTSD. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If this story has been told before, no matter: Willis reins in the mannerisms and the one-liners and fashions something far removed from anything he ever played subsequently: a sad, lonely survivor, withdrawn from the world, passively shuffling through life. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;            &lt;iframe width="440" height="260" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/JcXn7zKY6I0?wmode=transparent&amp;amp;start=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;                      &lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Willis’ role as Butch Coolidge, the ageing boxer in Quentin Tarantino’s epoch-defining neo-noir Pulp Fiction (1994) has perennially been overshadowed by the more showy turns by John Travolta and Samuel L. Jackson. But go back and watch the film again: Willis is both crumpled and brutal, exposed and ruthless. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tarantino cast him deliberately: “Bruce has the look of a 50s actor. I can’t think of any other star that has that look,” &lt;a href="https://books.google.com.au/books?id=c5SdiFJmswcC&amp;amp;pg=PA68&amp;amp;lpg=PA68&amp;amp;dq=%22Bruce+has+the+look+of+a+50s+actor.+I+can%27t+think+of+any+other+star+that+has+that+look.%22&amp;amp;source=bl&amp;amp;ots=N1GOXJHwk1&amp;amp;sig=r71zK1h5RYUXuAYZAGB10N_lc20&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=%22Bruce%20has%20the%20look%20of%20a%2050s%20actor.%20I%20can't%20think%20of%20any%20other%20star%20that%20has%20that%20look.%22&amp;amp;f=false"&gt;he said&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Willis’ scenes with Ving Rhames in the basement of the sleazy pawn shop sit at the heart of the film, while his interactions with Maria de Medeiros as his girlfriend Fabienne are gentle and blackly comic. It gave Willis’s career a shot of adrenaline, and showed others in Hollywood how star power (and a significant pay cut) could exist within American independent cinema.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;            &lt;iframe width="440" height="260" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/5lL1ypndnWA?wmode=transparent&amp;amp;start=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;                      &lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;We all know the twist to The Sixth Sense (1999) by now. But M. Night Shyamalan’s supernatural thriller should perhaps be better remembered for Willis’s measured and understated performance as Malcolm Crowe, a child psychologist whose patient can talk to the dead. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Malcolm’s assumptions are wrong in this film, just as ours are: one of the most memorable aspects of Willis’s performance is that, as an actor, he knows the twist from the start, but as the character he does not.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The film’s muted visual design and slow-burning pace is mirrored perfectly by the actor. Shyamalan’s camera zooms and tracks drop clues, but Willis never lets on.  He would work again with Shyamalan in Unbreakable (2000), a clever twist on the superhero genre.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;            &lt;iframe width="440" height="260" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/3-ZP95NF_Wk?wmode=transparent&amp;amp;start=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;                      &lt;/figure&gt;&lt;h2&gt;A career cut short&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The aphasia diagnosis now allows us to reflect on his career choices differently. Indeed, as the &lt;a href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/movies/story/2022-03-30/bruce-willis-aphasia-memory-loss-cognitive-disorder"&gt;Los Angeles Times reported&lt;/a&gt;, his co-workers have been expressing concerns about his work for many years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is a shame we shall not see directors experiment with Willis’s persona and deconstruct it in interesting ways like Michael Mann did with Tom Cruise in Collateral (2004) or Darren Aronofsky with Mickey Rourke in The Wrestler (2008).  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It now seems likely Willis’s swansong will be the yet to be released Paradise City, a crime thriller set in Hawaii seeing him reunited with John Travolta nearly 30 years after Pulp Fiction. Let’s see if that self-aware, easy-going, cool vibe remains intact.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;img src="https://counter.theconversation.com/content/180502/count.gif" alt="The Conversation" width="1" height="1" /&gt;&lt;p class="fine-print"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span&gt;Ben McCann does not work for, consult, own shares in or receive funding from any company or organisation that would benefit from this article, and has disclosed no relevant affiliations beyond their academic appointment.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
        <summary>Stepping back from acting after a diagnosis of aphasia, Bruce Willis will perhaps be best remembered from Die Hard. Here are some other films where he shone.</summary>
        <author>
            <name>Ben McCann, Associate Professor of French Studies, University of Adelaide</name>
            <foaf:homepage rdf:resource="https://theconversation.com/profiles/ben-mccann-398197"/>
        </author>
        <rights>Licensed as Creative Commons – attribution, no derivatives.</rights>
    </entry>
</feed>